All right, welcome back to 006
Dynamic Programming. We're now
in step two out of four.
Going to see a bunch more examples, three more examples of that dynamic
programming. Longest common subsequence, longest increasing subsequence, and
kind of a made up problem
from 006, alternating coin game.
And through those examples, we're going to explore a few new ideas, things
we haven't seen in action before yet. Dealing with multiple sequences
instead of just one, dealing with substrings
of sequences instead of prefixes and suffixes,
parent pointers so we can recover
solutions, like in shortest paths.
And a big one, which will mostly be fleshed out in the
next lecture, is subproblem constraint and expansion.
This is all part of
the sort bot paradigm.
Remember, subproblems,
relations,
topological order, base case,
original problem, and time.
Here is subproblems and relations. I've written down both what these things
are and the sort of key lessons we got from the first dynamic programming
lecture. Namely, we want to split up our problem into multiple subproblems.
And if your input is a sequence, that's the main case we've seen so far,
like the bowling
problem, for example,
then the natural subproblems we're going to
try are prefixes, suffixes, or substrings.
Prefixes and suffixes are nice because there's few of them. There's
only a linear number of them. In general, we want a polynomial number.
Sometimes you can get away with one of
these. They're usually about the same.
Sometimes you need substrings.
There's quadratically many of those.
Then once you set up
the subproblems, which
it's easy to set up subproblems,
but hard to do it right. To test whether you did it
right is, can I write a recurrence relation that relates
one subproblem solution to
smaller subproblem solutions?
And the general trick for doing this is to identify some feature of the
solution you're looking for. So you're trying to solve some subproblem.
And you try to ask a question whose answer would let you reduce to a
smaller subproblem. So if you can figure out what that question is, and that
question only has a polynomial number of answers, then boom. And you've
only got polynomial number of subproblems, then you will get a polynomial
running time.
I think another
way to say this, we just locally brute force all possible answers to
whatever question we come up with, as long as there's polynomially many.
And then each of them is
going to recursively call
the smaller subproblems. But because we memoize, we'll only solve each
subproblem once. And so in the end, the running time will be at most the
number of subproblems times the non
-recursive work done in that relation.
For that to work, of course, the relations
between subproblems must be acyclic.
So we'd like to give an explicit topological
order. Usually it's a couple of for loops.
But this is a topological
order in the subproblem DAG,
which I defined somewhat informally last time. But the vertices are
subproblems. And I want to draw an edge from a smaller problem to a bigger
problem, meaning
that if
evaluating B in this relation calls A, then I'll draw an arrow from A
to B, from the things I need to do first to the things I'll do later.
And the topological order
will be ready by the time I try to
compute B. I will have already computed A.
And of course, the relation
also needs base cases.
And then sometimes the original problem we
want to solve is just one of those subproblems.
Sometimes we need to combine multiple. We'll see
that today. So that's review of this framework.
And let's dive into
longest common subsequence.
It even has applications to things like computational biology. You
have two DNA sequences. You want to measure how in common they are.
One version of that, you might
see other versions in recitation,
called edit distance. This is sort of a simplest,
cleanest version where I give you two sequences. I have an
example here.
So for example, it could
be a sequence of letters.
So my first sequence
spells hieroglyphology,
study of hieroglyphs.
And second sequence
spells Michelangelo.
And what I'd like is a subsequence. So remember,
substring has to be some continuous range,
some interval.
Subsequence, you can take
any subset of the letters
in your sequence or any subset of the items in your sequence.
So you can have blanks in between. You can skip over items.
And so what we want
is the longest sequence
that is a subsequence of both the first string, the first sequence, and
the second string. And if you stare at this long enough, the longest common
subsequence, I don't think it's unique, but
there is a longest common subsequence, which
is hello, hiding in there.
And that is a longest
common subsequence.
So given that
input, the goal is to
compute hello, or whatever the longest common subsequence
is. So we're given, write this down carefully,
given two sequences,
let me name them, A and B.
We want to find the
longest sequence L
that's a subsequence
of both A and B.
So that's the
problem definition.
And we're going to see how to
solve it using dynamic programming.
And
whereas in the bowling
problem, we just had a single,
sequence of numbers,
the values of the bowling
pins, here we have two sequences.
And so we need a new trick.
Before we said, OK,
if our input consists of a single sequence,
we'll try prefixes, suffixes, or substrings.
Now we've got two sequences. So somehow we
need to combine multiple inputs together.
And so
here's a general trick.
Some problems for
multiple inputs.
It's a very simple trick.
We just take the product,
multiply
the subproblem spaces.
In the sense of
cross product of sets,
and in particular from an
accommodatorial perspective,
so we have sort of two inputs, the
first sequence A and the second sequence B.
For each of them, there's a natural choice, or there's three natural choices.
We could do one of these. I will choose suffixes for A and suffixes for
B. You could do some other combination,
but that would be enough for here.
And then I want to multiply these spaces, meaning the number of subproblems
is going to be the product of the number of suffixes here times the
number of suffixes here.
And in other words, every subproblem
in LCS is going to be a pair of suffixes.
So let me write that down.
So for LCS,
our subproblems are
L of ij.
This is going to be the longest common subsequence of the
suffix of A starting at i and the suffix of B starting at j.
And just to be clear
how many there are,
I'll give the
ranges for i and j.
Not going to assume the sequences are
the same length, like in the example.
So I'll write lengths of A and lengths of B. I like to include the empty
suffix. So when j equals the length of B, that's zero items in it, because
that makes for really easy base cases. So
I'd like to include those in my subproblems.
So that was the S in sort bot.
Now I claim that that set of
subproblems is enough to do a relation,
recursive relation among them.
So I'd like to solve
every subproblem Lij.
And relation is actually pretty simple, but
it's maybe not so obvious. So the idea is
because we're looking at suffixes, we should always
think about what happens in the first letter.
Because if we remove that first
letter, then we get a smaller suffix.
If you're doing prefixes, you should always look at the
last letter. Either one would work for this problem.
So we're doing suffixes. So we
look at A of i, and we look at B of j.
That's the first letter in the suffix A
starting at i and the suffix B starting at j.
And there are two cases. They
could be equal or different.
I think the easier case to think
about is when they're different.
So like in hieroglyphology and Michelangelo, if we look at the whole
string, say, the first letter in the top one is H. The first letter in the
second one is M. Those
are different letters.
And one of those letters is
not in the common subsequence
because they don't match.
I can't start with an H. Well, I can start with
an H. I could start with an M, but I can't start
with both.
One of those letters is not
in the output. In this example,
it's M.
But I don't know which one.
So I have this question.
I want to identify
some question.
And the question is, do I know that the H is not in the answer, or do I
know that M is not in the answer, the final longest common subsequence?
We don't know which,
so we'll just try both.
And then we're trying to maximize the length of
our common subsequence. So we'll take the max
of Li plus 1j and Li
j minus 1.
So the intuition here is
one of,
at least one,
of Ai and Bj is not in the LCS.
Get this wrong. j plus 1. Sorry.
Thinking about
substrings already.
Yeah, these are the beginning points. So I want to exclude the i -th letter.
So if Ai is not in, then I want to look at the suffix starting at i plus
1. If Bj is not in, then I want to
look at the suffix starting at j plus 1.
So the indices are always
increasing in the function calls.
And the other case
is that they're equal.
So this one, I have a little
bit harder time arguing.
I'm going to write the answer and
then prove that the answer is correct.
Here, I claim you don't
need to make any choices.
There's no question
you need to answer.
You can actually guarantee that Ai and Bj might
as well be in the longest common subsequence.
And so I get one point for that.
And then I recurse on all the remaining letters.
So from i plus 1 on and from j plus 1 on.
Why is this OK?
Well, we have a, b.
We're starting at position i
and starting at position j for b.
And
think of some optimal solution, some longest
common subsequence. So it pairs up letters
in
some way. This would be some non
-crossing pairing between equal letters.
And
let's say, so first case is that maybe i and j aren't paired with anything.
Well, that's silly. Because if they're not paired with anything, you have
some pairing on the rest of the items. You can add this pair. And
that would be a longer subsequence. So that would be a contradiction.
If we're imagining some
hypothetical optimal solution,
it has to pair one of these with something.
Maybe it pairs i with something else, though.
Well, if we have a longest common subsequence
that looks like that, I can just instead pair i
with Bj.
That's still, if
I had this pairing,
I'm actually not using any of these letters.
So why don't I just use this letter instead?
So you can argue there is a longest
common subsequence that matches Ai with Bj.
And so then we can guarantee,
by that little proof,
that we get one point
for matching them up.
That we don't have to
max this with anything.
So
two cases, pretty
simple formula.
And then we're basically done. We just
need to fill in the rest of sort bot.
So next is topological order.
So this I'll write as for loops.
Because I'm dealing with suffixes, we want to start with the empty suffixes
and then work our way to larger and larger suffixes. So this might seem
backwards. If you're
doing prefixes,
it would be an increasing order.
There's all sorts of orders. You could flip the i and j. It's very symmetric,
so it doesn't really matter. But anything that's generally decreasing
in i and j is good.
Then we have base cases.
These are when one of
the sequences is empty.
I don't care how many items are in B. But if A has
no items, there's no common subsequence. I mean,
it's empty.
And same for no
matter how big A is,
if I've exhausted
the B string, I start
from beyond the last item,
then I should get 0.
Then the original
problem we want to solve
is L0, 0.
That's just longest
common subsequence
of the entire A
and the entire B.
And time.
Because they are smaller subproblems, they're already
dealt with when I multiply by the number of subproblems.
So I just care about this max
computation and this equality check.
And we'll say those
each cost constant time.
So this is
quadratic time.
If the two strings are size n, this is n squared. In
general, it's the product of the two string sizes.
And that's longest
common substring.
So pretty straightforward.
Other than this little argument and
understanding the case when they're equal,
the easy case when they're unequal, we just try the only two things we
could do. One of A i and B j is not in the longest common subsequence.
So what I like to say is we guess which of those is the correct one that
is not in the longest common subsequence. And if we guess that it's in A,
then we'll recurse on that side. If we guess that
it's in j, then we'll recurse by increasing j.
And then I'd like to assume, not really, that we always make the correct
guess, that we made the correct choice whether it's i or j. Now, we don't
actually know how to do that. So instead, we brute force. We try both
of them. And then because we're trying to maximize, we take the max.
Just another way of
thinking about it.
But overall, very straightforward. The only
added complication here is we had to deal with
two sequences simultaneously. And we just
took the product of those. Pretty easy.
In general, if you have some constant number of sequences,
you can afford to do this. You'll still get polynomial.
But of course, once you go to n sequences, you can't
afford this. You would get like an n to the n behavior.
So that's kind of a limit
to how far you could go.
Two sequences is fine. Three
sequences is fine. But n sequences,
there probably is no polynomial
time algorithm for this problem.
Cool. I wanted to
show you an example.
I have an example here.
I didn't want to draw
hieroglyphology versus Michelangelo.
So I came up with
another example.
Their habit is to say hi. So the longest
common subsequence of their and habit is hi.
And I mean, it's a giant. Well, not that
giant. It looks kind of like a grid graph.
The base cases are out here
because those correspond.
So when I say this, each of these nodes is a subproblem.
And this corresponds to what is the longest common
subsequence between
EIR and abit.
And it should be i. It's the only letter they have in common. And that's
why there's a 1 here to say that the longest common subsequence has a 1, has
size 1.
The base cases are when either their has been emptied or when
habit has been emptied. So those all have zeros on the outside.
And then the problem we care about
is this one. It's their versus habit.
Claim is the length is 2.
And what I've drawn in here
is what I'll call parent pointers, like we talked
about with BFS and shortest paths and so on.
So we had this choice.
Sometimes we had a choice on whether we recursed
here or recursed here was the best thing to do.
And so I'll just draw in red the arrow from LIJ, sorry, to LIJ from
one of these in this case. And in this case, there was no choice.
I just draw in red that arrow.
So these diagonal edges are exactly the cases
where the letters match. Here, h equals h.
i equals i here. So I draw this diagonal edge. That's that first case
where the letters are equal. And so I recurse by increasing i and j.
That's why I get a diagonal edge. There's
also one over here where t equals t.
So for those, we're getting a 1 plus. You see this 1 is 1 larger than
the 0. This 2 is 1 larger than the 1. This 1 is 1 larger than the 0.
And for every other vertex,
we are recursing
this way and this way.
We see what those two numbers
are, and we take the max.
So this whole diagram
is just filled in
for each position where they're not equal. We look at the guy below. We
look at the guy to the right. Those are the slightly smaller substrings. We
look at those values.
We take the max.
And as long as you compute
this in a generally right
left and bottom up fashion,
whenever you're trying to compute a guy, you will have its predecessors
already computed. That's the topological order of this graph.
And then at the end, we get our answer, which is 2. And now if we pay
attention to where we came from, for example, this vertex had to come from this
direction. 2 is
the max of 2 and 1.
So I highlight the 2 edge.
And if I follow this path,
there should be a unique
path to some base case.
And in this case, the diagonal edges correspond
to my matching letters. So there's the h
here followed by the i here. And so hi is our longest common
substring. In general, we just follow these pointers backwards,
the red pointers, and we get our answer. So not only do we compute
the length of the LCS, but we actually can find the LCS using
parent pointers.
And this is a concept you can use in most dynamic
programs, including all the ones from today.
Any questions about LCS?
All right.
It's perfectly clear to
everyone in the audience.
So we move. Oh, yeah.
Now we move on to longest
increasing subsequence, which did
I lose a page here?
I just
disordered them.
This problem has almost the same name,
but it's quite different in behavior.
Longest
increasing subsequence.
LIS instead of LCS.
Both famous problems,
examples of dynamic programming.
Here we're just
given one sequence,
like carbohydrate.
So this is a sequence of letters. And I want to find the longest subsequence
of this sequence that is increasing, strictly increasing, let's say. So
in this case, alphabetically.
So I could include CR, for example, but not
CB. That would be a descending subsequence.
And in general,
or in this example,
the right answer,
or a right answer,
is abort.
There aren't very many English words that are increasing,
but there are some. And I looked through all of them.
As I just implemented this dynamic program we're about to write down, it
took me like two minutes to write down the DP, and then more work to read
the dictionary and
look for cool examples.
So in general, we're
given some sequence A.
And we want to find the longest increasing subsequence
of A. The longest sequence that is increasing,
strictly.
We could use the same thing to
solve not strictly increasing.
So here, things are going to be a little trickier. It's easy in that we
just have a single sequence. So again, we think, OK, let's look at our chart
here. We could try prefixes, suffixes, or substrings.
I personally prefer suffixes. Jason prefers prefixes.
Whatever you prefer is fine.
But I'll generally start there.
Because there's nothing in this problem that makes me think I need
to delete things from both ends. One question. Yeah, question.
Isn't the answer to
this problem always 26?
So is the answer
always, at most, 26?
Yes, if you're dealing with English words. So when I say
sequence here, this is a sequence of arbitrary integers,
word size integers. So there you can have a ton
of variety. This is just for the fun of examples.
I've drawn this. But even if the answer is 26,
finding that longest common subsequence is,
the obvious algorithm would be
to take all substrings of size 26,
which is like n to the 26.
So we're going to do much faster
than that here. n squared time.
And then if you remove
the strictly increasing,
then it can be
arbitrarily large.
OK. So let's try to do this.
I'm going to have some
mystic to write attempt here.
Let's just go for it.
So I want some subproblems.
And I'm going to choose suffixes.
So I'm going to define l of i
to be the longest increasing subsequence
of the suffix of a starting at i.
OK. That's the
obvious thing to do.
And now I'm going to
leave myself a little space.
And then I'd like a relation
on these.
So I'm going to
say what l of i is.
And what do I have to work with? Well, I have l of
things larger than i. Those would be smaller suffixes.
But let's go back to what is a question that I could ask about this subproblem
that might help me figure out what the longest increasing subsequence
looks like.
So we're looking at a,
here's a, from i on.
Longest increasing subsequence is sub
-subsequence. And we'd like to remove letter i.
Now when we do that, there are two choices. Maybe i is in the longest
increasing subsequence, or it's not in. So the question I would like to answer
is,
is
i in the longest
increasing subsequence of a,
of a from i onwards?
This is a binary question. There are two options. So again,
just like before. And so I can brute force those two options.
The trouble, and then I want the
longest one. So I'm going to take the max.
So I'd like to take the max of something like li plus 1. So in the
case that I don't put i in the solution, that's fine. Then I just look
at i plus 1 on and recursively compute
that. And that would be my answer.
And the other option is that I do put i in the
longest increasing subsequence. So I do 1 plus
the rest.
So i plus 1.
If I close this brace,
this would be a very strange recurrence, right? Because this is always bigger
than this one. So there's something wrong here. And the something wrong
is I
haven't enforced increasing at all. There's no constraints here. It's
just saying, well, I'll put i in, and then I'll do whatever remains.
And I'll pray that that's
increasing. Probably won't be.
Because indeed, if i is
a letter or is a number that is strictly greater than i plus 1, then this
will be wrong. So I really can't always do this. I need to somehow know.
I could check whether i plus 1 is in the
answer. But I don't know. Maybe i plus 1.
So I can check whether the letter
i is less than the letter i plus 1.
But maybe I put this in the longest increasing subsequence. And then I put
this in the longest increasing subsequence. And so I need to compare these
two items. But I don't know
when that's going to happen.
Things seem really hard.
There's no way from this subproblem
definition to write down a relation.
But there is a slight tweak to
this definition that makes it work.
So
the trouble we have here, and this is the
idea of subproblem constraints or conditions,
the trouble we have is when we recursively compute the longest
increasing subsequence on the remainder, we don't know the first
item in that answer.
Maybe it's i plus 1. Maybe
it's some guy over here.
If we knew who it was, then we
could compare that item to item i.
And so what we'd like to do is add a constraint to this subproblem that
somehow lets us know where the longest increasing subsequence starts.
So what I would like to say is longest
increasing subsequence of that suffix that starts
with a of i.
So in other words,
it includes a of i.
This was a separate question.
This is a bit of a funny
constraint. It changes the problem.
It's no longer what
we want to solve.
It's a terminal problem
before it was solving l of 0. We just want the longest increasing subsequence
of the whole thing. Now it's not necessarily l of 0. l of 0 means what
is the longest increasing
subsequence of the whole sequence a
that includes the
first letter of a.
And maybe we do include the first letter of a. Maybe we don't. We don't
know where the longest increasing subsequence starts. Here, for example, it
didn't. It started
at the second letter.
But conveniently,
it's OK that we don't know because
that's just another question we could ask
is where do we start?
Where might the LIS start? It could start at the first
letter, second letter, third letter. There's only n choices.
And let's just take
the max of all of them.
So before I get to the relation,
let's solve this problem.
I just want the max of l of i
for all i.
I guess we've been
writing sides of a here. OK,
the maximum will be the overall longest increasing subsequence. So if I
could find longest increasing subsequence that includes the first letter or
the longest one that includes the second letter and so on, so it starts at
the first letter, starts at the second letter, then this max will be the
longest overall.
So this subproblem is not what I really wanted, but it's still good enough
because it lets me solve my original problem. And this is adding an extra
constraint
to my subproblem. And doing this is challenging. Thinking about what the
right constraint that would let you solve your problem is tricky, especially
in the beginning.
But for now, let's just take this as
a thing that works. Why does it work?
Because now I
can say, well,
this term was fine,
max.
So I'm trying to
write longest increasing subsequence
starting with the ith letter versus,
yeah, actually, no, this is
just going to be different.
OK,
so now I get to the central issue, which is I know by the definition of l
of i that I include letter i. This is going to be in my longest increasing
subsequence. That's what I'm
looking for by this definition.
But
I don't know what
the second letter is.
Could be i plus 1, could be i
plus 2, could be anything bigger.
Whenever there's something I
don't know, I'll just brute force it.
I don't care. I don't care that I don't know. I'll just take a max over
all the possible choices. Let's say that the next letter included in the
longest increasing
subsequence i is j.
Then I would like to look at l of j. Now, I don't know what j is, but
I'll just brute force all possible choices for j. So it's going to be i
strictly less than j because I don't
want to include the same letter i again.
And otherwise, I would get an infinite recursive
loop if I put less than or equal to here.
And maybe I don't do
anything else up to n.
And OK, not quite done.
Now, this is the interesting
part. I can enforce increasing
because I can't just choose
any letter j to the right of i.
Also,
the number or letter that's written in here has to be greater than the
number that's written here. That's the strictly increasing property.
So I can add as a constraint
in this max
to say
a of i is strictly less than a of j. And if you wanted
non -strictly increasing, you would add an equal there.
OK, this is mathematical
notation. In Python, you would
say max open paren of this thing
for j in this range if this holds.
So I'm just doing the for loop.
And I only look at the possible choices for
j when the strict increasing property holds.
And then when that holds,
I check this. Now, this set might be empty. I
need to define what the max is when it's empty.
Then I will just say, oh, I also need a
1 plus, don't I? Let me just do 1 plus.
So we're told that i is in
the answer. So we always get 1.
The remainder is this or 0.
If there are no
aj's greater than ai,
then we'll default
to 0 and say, eh,
that i is the only
item in
my increasing subsequence.
OK, so there are a few details to get, right? But in general, once you
figure out what these recurrences look like, they're very simple. And this is
one line of code.
And then all you need
in addition to this
is the original
subproblem and
some other things.
We need the
base cases.
But I should do them in order.
Topological order is just the usual
for loop because I'm doing suffixes.
It's going to be i
equals length of a
down to 0. Base case is going to
be l of length of a, which is 0.
So there's no letters in that suffix.
And
we already did o.
And then time.
OK, this is a little different
from the past examples.
So the number of subproblems,
just like usual, is linear,
length of a.
Oops.
There's only one sequence
we're thinking about now,
unlike the previous example. But the work we're doing in this relation
now is nontrivial work. Before, we were just guessing among two different
choices.
Now we're guessing among up to n different
choices. This n here is length of a.
And so
we have theta length of
a non -recursive work
that we're doing
in each subproblem.
Or you might think of this as
choices that we're considering.
And for each choice, we're just spending. I mean, we're just taking a max
of those items, adding 1. So that's a constant overhead. And so we just get
this product,
which is a squared.
So that's longest
increasing subsequence.
Make sure I didn't
miss anything else.
So we're using this
idea of asking a question
and guessing or brute forcing
the answer to that question
in two places.
One place is we're requesting that the
longest increasing subsequence starts at i.
So then the question is,
well, what is the very second
item that's in the longest increasing subsequence
that starts with i? We're calling that j.
And we're brute forcing all the
possible choices that j could be,
which conveniently lets us check, confirm that it's
actually an increasing subsequence locally from i to j.
And then L of j will take care of the rest by induction. The rest of the
longest increasing subsequence starting at j will also be increasing.
And so this guarantees by induction
the whole thing will be increasing.
Then we also use this
local brute force to solve the original problem. So we added this constraint
of starting at i, but we didn't actually know overall where to start.
But that's fine, because there's only eight choices.
So I should mention, in the running time analysis,
so there's solving
the subproblems.
That's fine. But then there's also a plus
whatever it costs to solve the original problem.
But that's OK.
That's length of a.
So this was all of this plus length
of a is still length of a squared.
OK, but if you're doing exponential work here, that would be bad. We have
to do some reasonable amount of work to solve the original problem in terms
of all the subproblems.
I have an example hiding here.
This is a little
harder to stare at.
Here I have empathy.
And this example doesn't have much empathy, because
the longest increasing subsequence of empathy is empty.
Empty is one of the few
English words that's increasing.
And the hard part here is drawing the DAG. I mean,
it's almost the complete graph. But we only draw edges
from smaller letters to bigger letters.
So we draw from e to m, from e to p,
from e not to a. There's
no edge from e to a. From e
to t, not from e to h, but yes, from e to y. And then we also
draw from e to the base case, which is there's no more letters.
That edge to the base
case corresponds to this 0,
or I guess this n,
where we say, ah,
let's just recurse.
Let's just throw away.
Actually, maybe we don't need
the union 0 there, in fact, because
we include l of n, which
is the empty substring.
Then
the definition of
l is a little funny.
What does it mean to
say you start with a of n?
You have to define a of n.
Right. a of n is not
defined. So that's not so nice.
So maybe I'll fix that.
And erase
equals case.
But I'm still going
to draw an edge there,
conceptually say, oh, we're
just done at that point.
That's the base case where
we have no string left.
Cool.
And when I said from to to, actually, I meant
the reverse. So the edges go from right to left.
And then what we're doing is looking
for the longest path in this DAG.
Longest path is maybe a problem
we've talked about in problem session.
Because it's a DAG,
well, longest path is the same thing as shortest path if you just negate
all the weights. There are no weights in this picture. So if you just put
negative 1 on all these edges
and ask for the shortest path
from the base
to anywhere,
so single source shortest
paths from this base,
then we would end
up getting this path,
which if you look at
it is EMPTY, empty.
And so that shortest path is indeed the right answer.
What I've drawn here is the shortest path tree.
So also, if you wanted the longest increasing subsequence starting
at a, then it is ATY, just by following the red arrows here.
And how do you get that? Just draw the parent pointers just like we did
before. I didn't mention this example can also be solved with shortest paths.
Once I construct this graph,
you can do the shortest
path from some base, I
don't know which one,
to here.
If you put negative 1
on all of the diagonal edges
and you put weight
0 everywhere else,
then that corresponds to the shortest path in that graph will correspond
to the longest, the path with the most diagonal edges. And that makes sense
because the diagonal edges are where
we actually get letters in common.
And so in this case, it's 2.
So both of these dynamic programs could instead of writing them as a
recursive thing with memorization or writing them bottom up as a for loop and
then doing the computation, you
could instead construct a graph
and then run DAG
shortest paths on it.
But the point is these
are the same thing.
It's just simpler to write the dynamic programming code
because it's just a for loop and then a recurrence,
which we were just
updating an array.
Because you already know what the topological order is, you
don't have to write a generic depth -first search algorithm,
take the finishing order, reverse it, and
then run DAG shortest paths with relaxation.
Much simpler to just write down the
recurrence once you've figured it out.
OK? But they are the
same in these examples.
In Fibonacci, for example, you cannot write Fibonacci as a single -source
shortest paths problem. But a lot of DPs you can write as a shortest paths
problem.
Just a connection
to things we've seen.
All right. Last example.
Last problem for today.
We'll do more next week.
Alternating coin game.
This is a two -player game.
We're going to find the
optimal strategy in this game.
So an example is, in general,
you have a sequence of coins.
And
we have two players.
They take turns.
So given coins of value
v0
to vn minus 1.
So it's a sequence.
They're given in
order, in some order.
For example, 5, 10, 125.
Not necessarily sorted order.
And the rules of the game
are we're going to take turns.
I'm going to take turns with you. I'm going
to use i and u to refer to the two players.
And so in each turn,
whoever's turn it is,
we get to choose either the first coin or
the last coin among the coins that remain.
So at the beginning, I can
choose 5 or 25. And I might think,
oh, 25 is really good. That's better than 5. I should choose that. But
then, of course, you're going next. And you're going to choose 100.
And you'll win the game. You'll get
more of the total value of the coins.
The strategy is to take the 5, because then the
100 is still in the middle. And so once I take 5,
you get to choose 10 or 25.
At this point, you probably prefer 25, because
that's better than 10. But whichever you choose,
I can take the 100.
And so I get 105 points.
And you're going
to get 35 points.
OK? Good example for me.
And what we're going to do, so that's easy for a simple example. But in
general, there are exponentially many strategies here. At each step, either
of us could go left or right.
Choose the leftmost
or the rightmost.
And we're going to give
a dynamic programming
algorithm that just
solves this fast.
I didn't mention.
So this algorithm is quadratic time. But it can be made n log n time. It's
a fun exercise. Using a lot of the data structure augmentation stuff we've
done, you can make this n log n.
This algorithm, I think, is
going to be n squared time.
So I won't write
the problem exactly.
But I think you know the rules.
Choose leftmost or rightmost
coin, alternating moves.
So I'd like to define
some subproblems.
And this is a problem that's very naturally a substring problem. If I just
looked at suffixes, that would deal great with if I'm deleting coins from
the left.
Delete coins only from the
right, that would give me prefixes.
But I'll tell you now, there's no dynamic programming
where the answer is suffixes and prefixes.
You can do suffixes or
prefixes. But if you need both,
you almost certainly
need substrings.
Because as soon as I
delete the first coin,
and then maybe you
take the second coin,
that's exactly the optimal strategy here. Now you have an arbitrary
substring in the middle. OK? But substrings are enough, because we're only
deleting from the ends.
We'll look at substrings.
So more precisely, this
is just the intuition,
we're going to define some generic
x of ij is going to be what is the
maximum
total value
I can get
from this game
if we play it on coins
of value
vi to vj.
So that's a substring.
So this is one way to write
down the subproblems. And it's also
a good way. I mean, you can write
down a relation on this definition
of subproblems. But I'm low on time. There's two ways to solve this
problem. This is a reasonable way, exploiting that the game is zero -sum.
But I'd like to change this a little bit to give you,
I think, what's a cleaner way to solve the problem,
which is to add a third coordinate to my subproblems.
So now it's parameterized by three things.
p here only
has two choices.
It's me or you.
And this gets at a point that's maybe
not totally clear from this definition.
Max total value that I can get
from this substring of coins. But
this is not obviously what I need. So obviously,
at the beginning, I want the whole string.
And I want to know what
my maximum value is. Fine.
And I go first in this
game. I didn't specify.
But I do.
Overloading i.
But as soon as I do a move, as soon as I take
the first coin, for example, it's now your turn.
And so I don't really want to know the maximum
total value that I would get if I go first.
I'd like to say if
player p goes first.
I'd really like to know what
happens in the case where you go first.
And so for some of the substrings, I want to know what happens when you go
first. And for some of them, I want to know what happens when I go first.
So if I move, it's your turn. And so we're going to
flip back and forth between p being me and p being you.
p, you.
So you don't have to parameterize by this.
There's a way to write the recurrence otherwise.
But this is, I think,
a lot more intuitive.
Because now we can do
a very simple relation,
which is as follows.
So I'm going to
split into two cases.
One is x of i, j, me.
And the other is x of i, j, you.
So x of i, j, me.
So I have some
substring from i to j.
What could I do? I could take the first
coin. Or I could take the second coin.
Which should I do? That's my question. What is my first move? Should
I take the first coin or the second coin? So this is my question.
What is the first move?
There are exactly two possible answers to that
question. So we can afford to just brute force them.
And take the max.
If we're moving, we want the maximum number of points we can get, maximum
total value of the two choices. So if I take from the i side, the left
side, that would
be x of i plus 1,
j.
And now, crucially,
we flip players.
And it's your turn.
And if I take from the j side,
that will make it j minus 1.
This is what I accidentally wrote
at the beginning of the lecture.
Also flip players.
So either I shrink on the i side or I shrink on the j side. Oh, I should
add on here the value of the coin that I get. And add on the value of the
coin that I took.
So this is an expression
inside the max.
That sum.
And if I take the max
of those two options,
that is my locally
brute forced best choice
of what are the total value of coins I will
get out of the remainder given the u start,
plus this coin that I took
right now in the first step
and for the two possible
choices of what that coin is.
What remains is how do we
define this x of i, j, u?
This is a little bit funnier.
But it's conceptually
similar. I'm going to write
basically the same
thing here, but with a me
instead of a u.
Because again, it flips.
This is if u go first, then
the very next move will be me.
So this is just the symmetric
formula here.
I can even put the braces in.
So far the same.
Now, I don't put in the plus vi. And I don't put in the plus
vj here. Because if you're moving, I don't get those points.
So there's an asymmetry in this definition. You could define it in different
ways. But this is the maximum total value that I would get if you start.
So in your first move,
you get some points. But I
don't get any points out of that.
So there's no plus
vi. There's no plus vj.
It's just you either choose the i -th coin or you choose
the j -th coin. And then the coins that remain, for me,
shrink accordingly.
Now,
you're kind of a pain in the ass. You're an adversary.
You're trying to minimize my score, potentially.
Because you're trying to maximize your score. This is a zero -sum game.
So everything that you get, I don't get. So if you want to maximize your
score, you're trying to minimize
my score. These are symmetric things.
And so if you think for a while,
the right thing
to put here is min.
From our perspective, we're imagining
what is the worst case that could happen,
no matter what you do.
And we don't have control over what you do. And so we'd really like
to see what score would I get if you chose the i -th coin? What
score do you get if
you chose the j -th coin?
And then what we get is going to be
the worst of those two possibilities.
So when we get to choose, we're maximizing. And this is
a general two -player phenomenon that when you choose,
we end up minimizing. Because that's
the saddest thing that can happen to us.
OK, this is one way to
write a recurrence relation.
We have, of course,
all of sort bot to do. So the topological order here is
in increasing length of substrings. So the t is increasing
j minus i.
Start with empty
strings. So base case is
that x of i,
i me.
Is vi.
So here, I'm inclusive in
both ends in this definition.
So there is a coin I can take at the end. But if you move last
and there's one coin left, then I don't get it. So it's 0.
Then we have the original
problem. That is xij me.
Sorry,
x0n. That's the entire coin set starting
with me. That was the problem I wanted to do.
And then the running
time we get is
the number of subproblems.
That's theta n squared
because we're doing substrings
times the amount of non -recursive work I do here.
That's just a max of two numbers. Very simple.
Constant time.
So this is quadratic.
Let me show you an example.
This is hard to draw.
But what I've described here is
called solution 2 in the notes.
5, 10,
125 in both directions. And what we're interested in is all
substrings. So over here, I've written the choice for i.
So we start at one of
these. And if you start here,
you can't end earlier than there. So that's
why we're in the upper diagonal of this matrix.
And then there's two versions of each problem, the white version and the
blue version just down into the right of it if you can't see what blue is.
This is the version where you start.
This is the version where I start.
And I've labeled here all of the different numbers.
Please admire because this took a long time to draw.
But in particular, we have 105 here, meaning
that the maximum points I can get are 105.
And that's the case because if
we look over
there, it is the max
of these two incoming values
plus
the vi that I get. So either I go to the left and
I take that item or I go down and I take that item.
The option here is
I went to the left
and took,
well, that's going to be tricky to do in time. The claim is that
the best answer here is to go here with the 100 and take the 5
because going down corresponds
to removing the last item.
If I went to the left, that corresponds to removing, sorry, the first item.
If I went to the left, that corresponds to removing the last item. So my
options are 10 plus 25,
which is 35,
100 plus 5, 105 wins.
So that's why there's a red edge
here showing that was my better choice.
And in general, if you follow these parent
pointers back, it gives you the optimal strategy
in what you should do. First, you should take the 5 is what this is saying
because we just clipped off the 5. We used to start here. Now we start
here in this subinterval.
Then
our opponent, to be
annoying, will take the 25.
Doesn't actually
matter, I think.
They'll take the 100. And then
they take the 10. And it's game over.
All the numbers here are how many points we get. It doesn't say how
many points the opponent gets. Of course, you could add that as well.
It's just the total
sum minus what we get.
Now let me come back to high
level here. What we're really doing
is subproblem expansion.
And this is an idea that we
will expand on next lecture.
And the idea is that sometimes you start with the obvious subproblems of
prefixes, suffixes, or substrings. Here, the obvious version was substrings
because we're removing from both ends. If
you don't know, probably suffixes or prefixes
are enough.
So we start there. But sometimes,
that's still not enough subproblems.
Here, as soon as we made a move, our problem almost turned
upside down because now it's your turn instead of my turn.
And that was just
annoying to deal with.
And so whenever you
run into a new type of problem, just build more subproblems. As
long as it stays a polynomial number, we'll get polynomial time.
And so here, we doubled the number of subproblems to just the B case and
the U case. And that made this recurrence really easy to write. In the
notes, you'll see a messier way
to write it if you don't do that.
In the examples we'll see next lecture,
we're going to do a lot more expansion, maybe
multiplying the number of
subproblems by n or n squared.
And this will give us,
it will let us add
more constraints
to
our subproblems like we did
in longest increasing subsequence.
We added this constraint
that we start with a particular item. The more subproblems we have, we can
consider more constraints because we'll just brute force all the possible
constraints that could apply.
We'll see more
of that next time.
That's it for today.